So this is Anna Hazare,
هذا هو آنا هازاري،
and Anna Hazare may well be the most cutting-edge
وقد يكون آنا هازاري أكثر ناشط
digital activist in the world today.
رقمي متطور في العالم اليوم.
And you wouldn't know it by looking at him.
ولن تعرفوا ذلك بالنظر إليه.
Hazare is a 77-year-old Indian anticorruption and social justice activist.
هازاري ناشط هندي عمره 77 عامًا ضد الفساد وباحث عن العدالة الاجتماعية.
And in 2011, he was running a big campaign
في 2011، كان يقود حملة
to address everyday corruption in India,
للتصدي للفساد اليومي في الهند،
a topic that Indian elites love to ignore.
الموضوع الذي تحب النخبة الهندية تجاهله.
So as part of this campaign,
لذلك كجزء من الحملة،
he was using all of the traditional tactics
كان يستخدم كل الوسائل التقليدية
that a good Gandhian organizer would use.
التي يستخدمها منسق غاندي جيد.
So he was on a hunger strike,
لذلك قام بالإضراب عن الطعام،
and Hazare realized through his hunger
وأدرك هازاري خلال فترة جوعه
that actually maybe this time,
أن في الوقت الحالي حقيقةً،
in the 21st century,
في القرن 21، قد يكون
a hunger strike wouldn't be enough.
الإضراب عن الطعام لا يكفي.
So he started playing around with mobile activism.
لذلك بدأ في ممارسة نشاطه عبر المحمول.
So the first thing he did is he said to people,
وكان أول شيء فعله أن قال للناس،
"Okay, why don't you send me
"حسنًا، لماذا لا ترسلون لي
a text message if you support
رسالة نصية إن كنتم تدعمون
my campaign against corruption?"
حملتي ضد الفساد؟"
So he does this, he gives people a short code,
هذا ما قام به، أعطى الناس كود مختصر،
and about 80,000 people do it.
وراسله حوالي 80.000 شخص.
Okay, that's pretty respectable.
حسنًا، ذلك معتبر جدًا.
But then he decides,
لكنه قرر،
"Let me tweak my tactics a little bit."
"لأنشّط تخطيطي قليلًا"
He says, "Why don't you leave me a missed call?"
يقول، "لماذا لا تتركون لي مكالمة فائتة؟"
Now, for those of you who have lived in the global South,
الآن، للذين قد عاشوا منكم في جنوب العالم،
you'll know that missed calls
سوف تعرفون أن المكالمات الفائتة
are a really critical part of global mobile culture.
جزء حساس حقًا في عالم ثقافة المحمول.
I see people nodding.
أرى أناسًا يوافقونني.
People leave missed calls all the time:
يترك الناس مكالمات فائتة طوال الوقت:
If you're running late for a meeting
لو كنت مسرعًا لتأخرك على اجتماع
and you just want to let them know that you're on the way,
وتريد أن تعلمهم أنك في الطريق
you leave them a missed call.
تترك لهم مكالمة فائتة.
If you're dating someone and you just want to say "I miss you"
لو كنت تواعد شخصًا ما وتريد فقط أن تقول
you leave them a missed call.
"أفتقدك" أترك مكالمة فائتة.
So a note for a dating tip here,
حسنًا ملاحظة، قد تكون نصيحة مواعدة،
in some cultures,
في بعض الثقافات،
if you want to please your lover,
إن كنت تريد أن تسعد حبيبك،
you call them and hang up. (Laughter)
اتصل به وأغلق المكالمة. (ضحك)
So why do people leave missed calls?
لذا لماذا يترك الناس مكالمات فائتة؟
Well, the reason of course is that
حسنًا، السبب بالطبع
they're trying to avoid charges
أنهم يحاولون تجنب التكلفة
associated with making calls and sending texts.
المرتبطة بإجراء المكالمات وإرسال رسائل نصية.
So when Hazare asked people to leave him a missed call,
لذلك حين طلب هازاري من الناس ترك مكالمة فائتة له،
let's have a little guess how many people actually did this?
دعونا نخمن قليلًا كم من الناس قام بذلك فعليًا؟
Thirty-five million.
خمسة وثلاثون مليون.
So this is one of the largest coordinated actions in human history.
إذا هذه واحدة من أكبر الحركات المنسقة في التاريخ البشري.
It's remarkable.
الأمر لافت للنظر.
And this reflects the extraordinary strength of the emerging Indian middle class
ويعكس هذا القدرة الغير عادية للطبقة الوسطى الهندية الناشئة
and the power that their mobile phones bring.
والقوة التي أتت بها تليفوناتهم المحمولة.
But he used that,
لكنه استخدم ذلك،
Hazare ended up with this massive CSV file of mobile phone numbers,
حصل هازاري على ملف ضخم من أرقام التليفونات،
and he used that to deploy
واستخدمها لنشر
real people power on the ground
قوة الناس الحقيقة على الأرض
to get hundreds of thousands of people out on the streets in Delhi
ليجعل مئات الآلاف من الناس يخرجون إلى الشوارع في دلهي
to make a national point of everyday corruption in India.
لوضع نهاية قومية للفساد اليومي في الهند.
It's a really striking story.
قصة مدهشة حقًا.
So this is me when I was 12 years old.
هذا أنا حين كنت أبلغ 12 عامًا.
I hope you see the resemblance.
آمل أن تشاهدوا التشابه.
And I was also an activist,
كنت ناشطًا أيضًا،
and I have been an activist all my life.
وقد كنت ناشطًا طيلة حياتي.
I had this really funny childhood
عشت طفولةً ممتعةً حقًا
where I traipsed around the world
حيث تسكعت حول العالم
meeting world leaders and Noble prize winners,
أقابل قادة العالم والفائزين بجائزة نوبل،
talking about Third World debt,
أتحدث عن ديون العالم الثالث،
as it was then called,
كما كانت تسمى،
and demilitarization.
ونزع السلاح.
I was a very, very serious child. (Laughter)
كنت طفلًا جادًا جدًا جدًا. (ضحك)
And back then,
وبالعودة إلى،
in the early '90s,
أوائل التسعينات،
I had a very cutting-edge tech tool of my own:
كانت بحوزتي أداةً تكنولوجية متطورةً جدًا:
the fax.
الفاكس.
And the fax was the tool of my activism.
والفاكس كان أداة نشاطي.
And at that time, it was the best way
وفي ذلك الوقت، كانت هذه أفضل
to get a message to a lot of people
طريقة لإرسال رسالة لأناس كثيرين
all at once.
جميعهم مرة واحدة.
I'll give you one example of a fax campaign that I ran.
سوف أعطيكم مثالًا من حملة فاكس أدرتها.
It was the eve of the Gulf War
كانت عشية حرب الخليج
and I organized a global campaign to flood the hotel,
نظمت حملة عالمية لغمر الفندق،
the Intercontinental in Geneva,
الانتركونتيننتال في جينيف،
where James Baker and Tariq Aziz
حيث كان جيمس بيكر وطارق عزيز
were meeting on the eve of the war,
يجتمعان عشية الحرب،
and I thought if I could flood them with faxes,
واعتقدت أنه لو قدرنا على إغراقهم بالفاكسات،
we'll stop the war.
سوف نوقف الحرب.
Well, unsurprisingly,
وكما هو متوقع،
that campaign was wholly unsuccessful.
فشلت الحملة تمامًا.
There are lots of reasons for that,
هناك أسباب عديدة لذلك،
but there's no doubt that one sputtering fax machine
لكن لا يوجد شك أن جهاز فاكس أخرقا واحدا
in Geneva was a little bit of a bandwidth constraint
في جينيف كان ضئيل الحدود النطاقية الترددية
in terms of the ability to get a message to lots of people.
من حيث المقدرة على استقبال رسالة من أناس كثر.
And so, I went on to discover some better tools.
ولذلك، عملت على اكتشاف بعض الأدوات الأفضل.
I cofounded Avaaz, which uses the Internet to mobilize people
أسست آفاز، الذي يستخدم الإنترنت لحشد الناس.
and now has almost 40 million members,
والآن لديه غالبًا 40 مليون عضو،
and I now run Purpose, which is a home for these kinds of
وأنا أدير الهدف، الذي هو وطن لكل تلك الأنواع
technology-powered movements.
من الحركات ذات القوة التكنولوجية.
So what's the moral of this story?
إذًا ما المغزى من هذه القصة؟
Is the moral of this story,
هل المغزى من هذه القصة،
you know what, the fax is kind of eclipsed by the mobile phone?
أتعرفون ماذا، الفاكس أحد الأنواع التي تم خسفها بالمحمول؟
This is another story of tech-determinism?
هذه قصة أخرى عن الحتمية التكنولوجية.
Well, I would argue that there's actually more to it than that.
حسنًا، أود أن أدَّعي أن هناك أكثر مما هو عليه حقيقةً.
I'd argue that in the last 20 years,
أود أن أدَّعي أنه في العشرين عامًا الأخيرة،
something more fundamental has changed
شيء أكثر أهمية من مجرد
than just new tech.
التكنولوجيا الجديدة قد تغير.
I would argue that there has been a fundamental shift
أود أن أدَّعي أنه قد حدث تحرك مهم
in the balance of power
في ميزان القوة
in the world.
في العالم.
You ask any activist how to understand the world,
تسألون أي ناشط كيف نفهم العالم،
and they'll say, "Look at where the power is,
وسوف يقول، "أنظر إلى حيث تكون القوة،
who has it, how it's shifting."
من يمتلكها، كيف تنتقل."
And I think we all sense that something big is happening.
وأعتقد أننا جميعًا نشعر أن شيئًا ما كبير يحدث.
So Henry Timms and I —
أنا وهنري تيمس ـــ
Henry's a fellow movement builder —
هنري مُنشئ حركة زميل ـــ
got talking one day and we started to think,
أجرينا حديث أحد الأيام وبدأنا التفكير،
how can we make sense of this new world?
كيف يمكن أن نجعل لهذا العالم الجديد معنى؟
How can we describe it and give
كيف يمكننا وصفه ونمنحه
it a framework that makes it more useful?
إطارًا يجعله أكثر نفعًا؟
Because we realized that many
لأننا أدركنا أن العديد
of the lessons that we were discovering in movements
من الدروس التي كنا نكتشفها في الحركات
actually applied all over the world
التي طُبقت فعليًا حول العالم
in many sectors of our society.
في قطاعات عديدة من مجتمعنا.
So I want to introduce you to this framework:
لذلك أريد أن أعرض لكم هذا الإطار:
Old power, meet new power.
تلتقي القوة القديمة والقوة الحديثة.
And I want to talk to you about what new power is today.
وأريد أن أحدثكم عن القوة الحديثة اليوم.
New power is the deployment
القوة الحديثة هي نشر
of mass participation and peer coordination —
مقدار مشاركة كبير وتنسيق الأقران ـــ
these are the two key elements —
هذان هما العنصران الأساسيان ـــ
to create change and shift outcomes.
لإحداث تغيير وتحويل النتائج.
And we see new power all around us.
ونرى الآن القوة الحديثة في كل مكان حولنا.
This is Beppe Grillo
هذا بيبي جريلو
he was a populist Italian blogger
كان مُدونًا إيطاليًا شعبويًا
who, with a minimal political apparatus and only some online tools,
بالحد الأدنى من الجهاز السياسي وبعض أدوات الإنترنت فقط،
won more than 25 percent of the vote
كسب أكثر من 25% من الأصوات
in recent Italian elections.
في انتخابات إيطالية مؤخرًا.
This is Airbnb,
هذا إير بي إن بي،
which in just a few years
الذي في سنوات قليلة فقط
has radically disrupted the hotel industry
قد عطل صناعة الفنادق
without owning a single square foot of real estate.
دون أن يكون مالكًا لقدم مربع واحد من الأرض.
This is Kickstarter,
هذا كيك ستارتر،
which we know has raised over a billion dollars
الذي كما نعرف جمع أكثر من مليار دولار
from more than five million people.
من أكثر من خمسة مليون شخص.
Now, we're familiar with all of these models.
الآن، نحن نألف كل هذه الأمثلة.
But what's striking is the commonalities,
لكن ما يدهش هو القواسم المشتركة،
the structural features of these new models
الخصائص البنائية لهذه النماذج الحديثة
and how they differ from old power.
وكيف اختلفت عن القوة القديمة.
Let's look a little bit at this.
دعونا ننظر قليلًا لهذا.
Old power is held like a currency.
أقيمت القوة القديمة مثل العملة
New power works like a current.
تعمل القوة الحديثة كتيار.
Old power is held by a few.
أقام القوة القديمة قليل.
New power isn't held by a few, it's made by many.
لم تقام القوة الحديثة بقليل، صنعت بالكثير.
Old power is all about download,
تعتمد القوة القديمة على التحميل،
and new power uploads.
والقوة الحديثة على الرفع.
And you see a whole set of characteristics that you can trace,
وترون مجموعة الخصائص بأسرها التي يمكنكم تتبعها،
whether it's in media or politics or education.
سواء كانت في الإعلام أو السياسة أو التعليم.
So we've talked a little bit about what new power is.
قد تكلمنا قليلًا عما هي القوة الحديثة.
Let's, for a second, talk about what new power isn't.
دعونا، لدقيقة، نتكلم عن ما هو ليس بالقوة الحديثة.
New power is not your Facebook page.
القوة الحديثة ليست صفحتك على الفيس بوك.
I assure you that having a social media strategy
أؤكد لكم أن امتلاك استراتيجية إعلام اجتماعي
can enable you to do just as much download
يمكن أن تتيح لك بإجراء كمية تحميلات بمقدار
as you used to do when you had the radio.
ما تعودت عليه حين كان لديك راديو.
Just ask Syrian dictator Bashar al-Assad,
فقط اسأل الديكتاتور السوري بشار الأسد،
I assure you that his Facebook page
أؤكد لكم أن صفحته على الفيسبوك
has not embraced the power of participation.
لم تتحصل على القوة من المشاركة.
New power is not inherently positive.
القوة الحديثة ليست إيجابية بفطرتها.
In fact, this isn't an normative argument that we're making,
في الواقع، هذه المناقشة التي نجريها ليست قياسية
there are many good things about new power,
هناك أشياء عديدة جيدة عن القوة الحديثة
but it can produce bad outcomes.
لكنها يمكن أن تكون سيئة النتائج.
More participation, more peer coordination,
مشاركة أكثر، تنسيق أقران أكثر،
sometimes distorts outcomes
أحيانًا يشوه النتائج
and there are some things,
وهناك بعض الأشياء،
like things, for example, in the medical profession
مثل الأشياء، على سبيل المثال، في مهنة الطب
that we want new power to get nowhere near.
التي نريد للقوة الحديثة أن تصل لأقرب مكان لها.
And thirdly, new power is not the inevitable victor.
وثالثًا، القوة الحديثة ليست منتصرة حتميًا.
In fact, unsurprisingly,
في الواقع، وليس مفاجأة،
as many of these new power models get to scale,
كما أن العديد من أمثلة القوة الحديثة هذه تحقق الانتشار الواسع،
what you see is this massive pushback
ما ترونه هو تلك المقاومة الهائلة
from the forces of old power.
من قوى القوة القديمة.
Just look at this really interesting epic struggle
فقط أنظروا لهذا الكفاح الملحمي المشوق حقًا
going on right now between Edward Snowden and the NSA.
القائم حاليًا بين إدوارد سنودين ووكالة الأمن القومي.
You'll note that only one of the two people on this slide
سوف تلاحظون أن شخصًا واحدًا فقط من الشخصين في الشريحة
is currently in exile.
حاليًا في منفى.
And so, it's not at all clear
ولذلك، ليس من الواضح
that new power will be the inevitable victor.
أن القوة الحديثة سوف تكون المنتصر الحتمي.
That said, keep one thing in mind:
الذي قال، احفظ شيئا واحد في عقلك:
We're at the beginning of a very steep curve.
نحن في بداية منحنى شديد الانحدار.
So you think about some of these new power models, right?
أنتم تفكرون في نماذج القوة الحديثة
These were just like someone's
صحيح؟ وكانت هذه الفكرة تماما مثل الجراج
garage idea a few years ago,
لشخص ما منذ بضع سنوات،
and now they're disrupting entire industries.
والآن يعطلون صناعات بأسرها.
And so, what's interesting about new power,
ولذلك، ما يمتع في القوة الحديثة،
is the way it feeds on itself.
الطريقة التي تغذي بها نفسها.
Once you have an experience of new power,
بمجرد أن يكون لديكم خبرة في القوة الحديثة،
you tend to expect and want more of it.
تميلون للتطلع وتريدون المزيد منها.
So let's say you've used a peer-to-peer lending platform
لذلك دعونا نقول أنكم قد استخدمتم منصة إقراض الند للند
like Lending Tree or Prosper,
مثل شجرة الإقراض أو التكاثر،
then you've figured out that you don't need the bank,
ثم اكتشفتم أنكم لستم بحاجة للبنك،
and who wants the bank, right?
ومن الذي يريد البنك، صحيح؟
And so, that experience tends to embolden you
وبعد ذلك، الخبرة تميل أن تجرأكم
it tends to make you want more participation
تميل أن تجعلكم تريدون مزيدا من المشاركة
across more aspects of your life.
عبر جوانب كثيرة من حياتكم.
And what this gives rise to is
ويعطي هذا الارتفاع
a set of values.
لمجموعة من القيم.
We talked about the models
نحن نتكلم عن النماذج
that new power has engendered —
التي قد أنشأتها القوة الحديثة ـــ
the Airbnbs, the Kickstarters.
الإير بي إن بي، والكيك ستارترز.
What about the values?
ماذا عن القيم؟
And this is an early sketch
وهذا رسم قديم
at what new power values look like.
عما تبدو عليه قيم القوة الحديثة.
New power values prize transparency above all else.
قيم القوة الحديثة تثمن الشفافية فوق كل شيء آخر.
It's almost a religious belief in transparency,
هي في الغالب عقيدة تؤمن بالشفافية.
a belief that if you shine a light on something,
أنا أؤمن بأنك لو صوبت الضوء على شيء ما،
it will be better.
سوف يكون أفضل.
And remember that in the 20th century, this was not at all true.
وتذكروا ذلك في القرن العشرين، هذا لم يكن صحيحًا إطلاقًا.
People thought that gentlemen should sit behind closed doors
أعتقد الناس أن السادة يجب أن يجلسوا خلف الأبواب المغلقة
and make comfortable agreements.
ويعقدون اتفاقيات مريحة.
New power values of informal, networked governance.
قيم القوة الحديثة من حكم شبكي غير رسمي.
New power folks would never have invented the U.N. today,
شعوب القوة الحديثة لن يخترعوا الأمم المتحدة أبدًا اليوم.
for better or worse.
للأفضل أو الأسوأ.
New power values participation,
القوة الحديثة تقدر المشاركة،
and new power is all about do-it-yourself.
والقوة الحديثة هي كل شيء عن أفعلها بنفسك.
In fact, what's interesting about new power
في الواقع، الممتع في
is that it eschews some of the professionalization
القوة الحديثة هو تجنب بعض من الاحتراف
and specialization that was
والتخصص اللذين كانا
all the rage in the 20th century.
الأكثر شعبية في القرن العشرين.
So what's interesting about these
لذلك ما يهم في هذه
new power values and these new power models
القيم للقوة الحديثة ونماذج القوة الحديثة
is what they mean for organizations.
هو ما يعنيان للمنظمات.
So we've spent a bit of time thinking,
لذلك قد قضينا جزء من الوقت نفكر،
how can we plot organizations
كيف يمكننا تخطيط المنظمات
on a two-by-two where, essentially,
جنبًا إلى جنب حيث، وأساسيًا،
we look at new power values
ننظر إلى قيم القوة الحديثة
and new power models
ونماذج القوة الحديثة
and see where different people sit?
ونرى أين يجلس الأشخاص المختلفون؟
We started with a U.S. analysis,
بدأنا بتحليل للولايات المتحدة،
and let me show you some interesting findings.
ودعوني أريكم بعض النتائج المشوقة.
So the first is Apple.
حسنًا الأول هو آبل.
In this framework, we actually described Apple
في هذا الإطار، نحن نصف آبل فعليًا
as an old power company.
كشركة قوة قديمة.
That's because the ideology,
ذلك بسب الأيديولوجية،
the governing ideology of Apple
الأيديولوجية الحاكمة في آبل
is the ideology of the perfectionist
هي أيديولوجية الكمال
product designer in Cupertino.
مصمم المنتجات كوبرتينو.
It's absolutely about that beautiful, perfect thing descending upon us
إنها تمامًا عن ذلك الشيء الجميل المثالي الذي يتنزل علينا
in perfection.
بكمال.
And it does not value, as a company, transparency.
ولا تُقدر، كشركة، الشفافية.
In fact, it's very secretive.
في الواقع، هو شديد السرية.
Now, Apple is one of the most succesful companies in the world.
الآن، آبل واحدة من أكثر الشركات الناجحة في العالم.
So this shows that you can
إذًا هذا يرينا أنه لا زلتم
still pursue a successful old power strategy.
تستطيعون متابعة استراتيجية قوة قديمة ناجحة.
But one can argue that there's real vulnerabilites in that model.
لكن يمكن أن يدعي شخص أن هناك عرضة للهجوم حقيقية في ذلك النموذج.
I think another interesting comparison
أعتقد مقارنة مشوقة أخرى
is that of the Obama campaign
من حملة أوباما
versus the Obama presidency.
ضد رئاسة أوباما.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, I like President Obama,
الآن، أنا معجب بالرئيس أوباما،
but he ran with new power at his back, right?
لكنه ترشح والقوة الحديثة تسانده، صحيح؟
And he said to people,
وقال للناس،
we are the ones we've been waiting for.
نحن الذين قد كنا ننتظرهم.
And he used crowdfunding
واستخدم التمويل الجماعي
to power a campaign.
لتشغيل الحملة.
But when he got into office,
لكن حين حصل على السلطة،
he governed like more or less all the other presidents did.
حكم مثل ما جميع الرؤساء الآخرين حكموا لا أكثر أو أقل.
And this is a really interesting trend,
وهذا اتجاه مشوق حقًا،
is when new power gets powerful,
حين تصبح القوة الحديثة قوية
what happens?
ماذا يحدث؟
So this is a framework you should look at
هذا إطار يجب أن تنظروا إليه
and think about where your own organization
وتفكروا أين تقع
sits on it.
منظمتكم به.
And think about where it should be
وتفكرون أين يجب ان تكون
in five or 10 years.
في 5 أو 10 أعوام.
So what do you do if you're old power?
حسنًا ماذا تفعلون لو أنتم قوة قديمة؟
Well, if you're there thinking, in old power,
حسنًا، لو أنتم هناك تفكرون، في القوة القديمة،
this won't happen to us.
هذا لن يحدث لنا.
Then just look at the Wikipedia entry for Encyclopædia Britannica.
ثم أنظروا إلى الموسوعة الحرة مدخل للموسوعة البريطانية.
Let me tell you, it's a very sad read.
دعوني أخبركم، إنها قراءة حزينة جدًا.
But if you are old power,
لكن لو أنتم قوة قديمة،
the most important thing you can do is to occupy yourself
الشيء الأكثر اهمية الذي يمكنكم فعله هو احتلال أنفسكم
before others occupy you,
قبل أن يحتلها الآخرون،
before you are occupied.
قبل أن تُحتلوا.
Imagine that a group of your biggest skeptics
تخيلوا مجموعة من أكبر مشككيكم
are camped in the heart of your organization
معسكرون في قلب منظمتكم
asking the toughest questions
يسألون أصعب الأسئلة
and they can see everything inside of your organization.
وهم يستطيعون رؤية كل شيء داخل منظمتكم.
And ask them, would they like what they see
واسألوهم، هل يعجبهم ما يرون
and should our model change?
وهل يجب تغيير نموذجنا؟
What about if you're new power?
ماذا عن لو أنتم قوة حديثة؟
Is new power kind of just riding the wave to glory?
هل القوة الحديثة فقط نوع من ركوب الموج للمجد؟
I would argue no.
أقول لا.
I would argue that there are some very real challenges
أدَّعي أن هناك بعض التحديات الحقيقة فعلًا
to new power in this nascent phase.
للقوة الحديثة في مرحلة النشأ هذه.
Let's stick with the Occupy Wall Street example for a moment.
دعونا نقف دقيقة مع مثال احتلوا وول ستريت.
Occupy was this incredible example of new power,
احتلوا كان هذا المثال الذي لا يصدق للقوة الحديثة،
the purest example of new power.
أنقى مثال للقوة الحديثة.
And yet, it failed to consolidate.
وبعد، فشل في التضامن.
So the energy that it created
الطاقة التي ولدتها
was great for the meme phase,
كانت هائلة لمرحلة النسخ،
but they were so committed to participation,
لكنها كانت قاتلة جدًا للمشاركة،
that they never got anything done.
ذلك لم يقوموا بإتمام أي شيء أبدًا.
And in fact that model
وفي الواقع ذلك النموذج
means that the challenge for new power is:
يعني أن التحدي للقوة الحديثة هو:
how do you use institutional power
كيف تستخدم القوة المؤسسية
without being institutionalized?
دون أن تكون مؤسسي؟
One the other end of the spectra is Uber.
نهاية الطرف الآخر من الطيف أوبر.
Uber is an amazing,
أوبر نموذج للقوة الحديثة،
highly scalable new power model.
مدهش ذو تدرجية عالية.
That network is getting denser and denser
تلك الشبكة تصبح أكثف وأكثف
by the day.
يومًا بعد يوم.
But what's really interesting about Uber is
لكن الممتع حقًا في أوبر هو
it hasn't really adopted new power values.
أنها لم تتخذ قيم القوة الحديثة فعليًا.
This is a real quote from the Uber CEO recently:
هذا اقتباس حقيقي من الرئيس التنفيذي لأوبر مؤخرًا:
He says, "Once we get rid of the dude in the car" — he means drivers —
يقول، "بمجرد أن نتخلص من الرجل في السيارة" ـــ يقصد السائقين ـــ
"Uber will be cheaper."
"أوبر سوف تكون أرخص."
Now, new power models live and die
الآن، نماذج القوة الحديثة تعيش وتموت
by the strength of their networks.
بقوة شبكاتها.
By whether the drivers and the consumers
بواسطة المحركين والمستهلكين على حد سواء
who use the service actually believe in it.
الذين يستخدمون الخدمة التي يؤمنون بها حقًا.
Because they're not an exercise of top-down perfectionism,
لأنها ليست تدريب للحد من الكمالية،
they are about the network.
إنها عن الشبكة.
And so, the challenge,
ولذلك، التحدي،
and this is why it's in no way surprising,
وهذا هو لماذا لا اندهاش من أي اتجاه،
is that Uber's drivers are now unionizing.
من أن محركي أوبر يتحدون الآن.
It's extraordinary.
إنها غير عادية.
Uber's drivers are turning on Uber.
محركو أوبر يشغلون أوبر.
And the challenge for Uber —
والتحدي لأوبر ـــ
this isn't an easy situation for them —
هذا ليس موقف سهل بالنسبة لهم ـــ
is that they are locked into a broader superstrcuture
هو أنهم قد حُبسوا داخل اوسع بنية فوقية.
that is really old power.
تلك حقًا قوة قديمة.
They've raised more than a billion dollars in the capital markets.
لقد رفعوا أكثر من مليار دولار في الأسواق الرأس مالية.
Those markets expect a financial return,
تتوقع هذه الأسواق عائدًا ماليًا
and they way you get a financial return
وطريقتهم للحصول على عائد مالي
is by squeezing and squeezing
هي القيام بعصر مستخدميهم ومحركيهم
your users and your drivers
أكثر فأكثر
for more and more value
لقيمة أكثر فأكثر
and giving that value to your investors.
وإعطاء تلك القيمة لمستثمريك.
So the big question about the future of new power, in my view, is:
إذًا السؤال الكبير عن مستقبل القوة الحديثة، من وجهتي، هو:
Will that old power just emerge?
هل القوة القديمة سوف تبرز؟
So will new power elites just become
إذًا هل نخبة القوة الحديثة سوف يصبحون
old power and squeeze?
قوة قديمة فقط ويندمجون؟
Or will that new power base bite back?
أم هل سوف تنقلب قاعدة القوة الحديثة؟
Will the next big Uber
هل أوبر الكبيرة القادمة
be co-owned by Uber drivers?
سوف يمتلكها محركو أوبر؟
And I think this going to be a very interesting
وأعتقد أن هذا سؤال بنائي
structural question.
مثير للاهتمام جدًا.
Finally, think about new power
في النهاية، فكر في القوة الحديثة
being more than just an
كونها أكثر من مجرد
entity that scales things
الكيان الذي يقيم الأشياء
that make us have slightly better consumer experiences.
التي تجعل لدينا تجارب مستهلكون أفضل قليلًا
My call to action for new power
دعوتي للعمل من أجل القوة الحديثة
is to not be an island.
هي ألا تكون جزيرة.
We have major structural problems in the world today
لدينا في العالم اليوم مشكلات هيكلية رئيسية
that could benefit enormously
يمكن أن تستفيد بشكل هائل
from the kinds of mass participation
من أنواع المشاركة الكبيرة
and peer coordination
وتنسيق الأقران
that these new power players
التي يعرف لاعبو القوة الحديثة
know so well how to generate.
كيف يولدونها بشكل جيد جدًا.
And we badly need them to turn their energies and their power
ونحن نحتاج بشدة إلى أن يوجهوا طاقتهم وقوتهم
to big, what economists might call
لأكبر، ما يمكن لأخصائيين الاقتصاد أن يدعوه
public goods problems,
مشكلات السلع العامة،
that are often beyond markets
التي غالبًا ما تكون خلف الأسواق
where investors can easily be found.
حيث يمكن للمستثمرين العثور عليها بسهولة.
And I think if we can do that,
وأعتقد أنه إن كنا نستطيع فعل ذلك،
we might be able to fundamentally change
قد يكون بمقدورنا أن نغير بشكل أساسي
not only human beings' sense of their own agency and power —
ليس فقط إحساس الجنس البشري بقوته وقدرته ـــ
because I think that's the most wonderful thing about new power,
لأني أعتقد أن أكثر شيء رائع في القوة الحديثة،
is that people feel more powerful —
هو شعور الناس بقوة أكبر ـــ
but we might also be able to change
لكنا يمكن أن يكون بمقدورنا تغيير
the way we relate to each other
طريقة تعاملنا مع بعضنا البعض
and the way we relate to authority and institutions.
وطريقة تعاملنا مع السلطات والمؤسسات.
And to me, that's absolutely
وبالنسبة لي، هذا يستحق بالتأكيد
worth trying for.
المحاولة من أجله.
Thank you very much.
أشكركم جدًا جدًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)